Guide to the Records of the Communications Workers of America, Local 1150 WAG.059
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America, Local 1150 Records
1939-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America. Local 1150 (New York, N.Y.)
Pratt, James J.
Unger, Laura
Whitley, Vinny
WAG.059
79 Linear Feet in 89 record cartons and manuscript boxes and one oversized folder.
2 websites in two archived websites.
This collection details the development of CWA Local 1150 (long-distance telephone workers employed by AT&T), and its history as a militant force in the New York-area communications industry. The local was divided into three sections: Traffic (operators), Plant (maintenance and technical) and Administrative (clerical, white collar); and the arrangement of the records often reflects these divisions. The collection includes correspondence, memos, reports, election records, bulletins, clippings, bargaining records and agreements, and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by James J. Pratt, the President of the Communications Workers of America, Local 1150, in 1987. The accession numbers associated with these materials are 1987.012 and 1987.015. Two additional groups were donated by Laura Unger, the President of the Communications Workers of America, Local 1150, in 1989 and 1992. In September 2019, Local 1150 President Vinny Whitley donated the accretion 2019.118. The following accession numbers are also associated with this collection: NPA.1992.001, NPA.1992.013, NPA.1993.007, NPA.2000.070, NPA.2000.078, NPA.2000.338, NPA.2005.068 and 2009.073.
Website was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2009 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive.. In 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2017, the original associated with this website, http://cwalocal1150.org/, became defunct. In 2018, the new URL, http://cwa1150.com/, was added to the web archive. The accession number associated with this URL is 2019.092.
Conditions Governing Access
Grievances are restricted for 75 years from the date of creation; all other materials are open to researchers without restrictions.
Historical Note
This collection presents an unusually full and detailed picture of the development of one of the major locals of the predominantly white-collar CWA. Local 1150 has been distinguished by its militant and imaginative stance in dealing with rapidly changing conditions in an industry dominated by a single powerful employer, the ATT System.
Long Lines telephone workers are those responsible for long-distance and overseas service; they operate and maintain the links between local telephone systems, and also handle various special services (e.g., radio and telegraph services to the press and other special clients) offered through the ATT system. From the beginning Long Lines services were largely based in New York City, and New York Long Lines workers formed the first, largest and most active union local in what was to become a separate department of ATT and a separate Bargaining Unit of the CWA.
Through the period covered by this collection half or more of all Long Lines workers were women. The New York Local was (and is) divided into three Sections representing a variety of job types and skill levels: Traffic (mostly operators), Plant (installation and maintenance), and Administrative (clerical and engineering). The first and third were largely female, while Plant was virtually all male. The relative sizes of the sections were roughly reflected in the composition of the Local's fifteen-person Executive Board: eight representatives from Traffic, three Plant, and four Administrative. All local officials, including unit stewards, were elected by the membership.
The post-World War I period saw the first stirrings of interest in union organization among telephone workers; these were headed off by the creation of a company union (the Telephone Workers Association) and by strict paternalistic oversight, especially of women workers. Despite a rigorous (and often unpaid) training period, high stress on the job, low pay, and little opportunity for advancement, telephone work was generally well regarded by women --at least as compared to other white-collar jobs open to them. The company counted on having a young female work-force with a high turnover rate and little solidarity or interest in union organizing. By 1941 ATT reported the average age for beginning operators as eighteen, and still routinely conducted interviews with applicants' parents before hiring.
A small group of militant and determined workers began efforts to organize in Long Lines in the mid-1930s. Passage of the Wagner Act in 1935 gave them the impetus to replace the company union with a genuinely independent local organization. They then faced the question of how to link up with other organized telephone workers. A series of national meetings and conventions in 1938-39 (reflecting deep division over local autonomy vs. a strong national union) resulted in the formation of the National Federation of Telephone Workers, a loosely-structured umbrella group. The New York Long Lines Local, by now 9,400 members strong and certified by the NLRB, was the third largest member of the Federation.
Impatience with progress at the national level led the New York Local to reorganize itself in 1940 as a component of a new body, the Federation of Long Lines Telephone Workers (FLLTW). The FLLTW became the focus of broader organizing efforts and negotiated its first contract with ATT in October 1940. The heroic (and essential) service of telephone workers during World War II, plus the constraints of wartime strike bans and wage freezes, left Long Lines workers eager for a more effective, militant program. In 1945 the FLLTW won a wage increase, setting the pace for other telephone workers. Seeking even greater bargaining strength, nine New York Long Lines locals then merged to form Local 1 of the FLLTW, which in turn revised its constitution and renamed itself the American Union of Telephone Workers (AUTW).
The period of the late 1940s was characterized by growing dissatisfaction with NFTW weakness and growing sentiment for the creation of a genuine national union and affiliation with the CIO. Opinion within the AUTW was still divided and for a while the CIO carried out its own organizing campaign among communications workers, through its Telephone Workers Organizing Committee (TWOC). In 1946 several telephone locals (including New York Long Lines) formed the Communications Workers of America, and they went on to lead a bitter two-month national strike in 1947. After a brief period of re-entry into the AUTW (now affiliated with the TWOC-CIO), Long Lines workers finally rejoined the CWA in 1949, as Local 1 of CWA Divison 10. In April 1951 New York Long Lines formally adopted its present title of Local 1150, CWA Division (now district) 1.
The years from 1949 through the 1970s saw a quickening pace of innovation and automation in the communications industry. The 1950s brought Electronic Switching Systems and wider use of co-axial cables, microwave communications, and data-processing machines. In the 60s Direct Distance Dialing and communications satellites were introduced, and the 70s brought laser and fiber optics technology. Although the ultimate effect of these changes was to be a drastically reduced Local membership, Local 1150 was able to win substantial gains during the first decades of its existence. Wages, working hours and seniority rights were improved, and the Local negotiated military service leaves and an overtime equalization plan that were models for the industry. Local 1150 also initiated a wartime Blood Bank program that resulted in the creation of a national Blood Bank for ATT employees. In 1952 a Local 1150 grievance resulted in the creation of a new title, Assistant Engineer, the highest-paid title in the Bargaining Unit.
The Local has participated in a number of strikes and has loyally supported the struggles of fellow workers. Members' refusal to cross Western Electric workers' picket lines in 1950 resulted in a lock-out, and the Local raised $56,000 to support a Southern Bell strike in 1956. Major national CWA strikes in 1971 and 1974 resulted in an agency shop agreement and a national contract.
Both automation and restructuring have posed persistent threats to the vitality of Local 1150. Beginning in the 1950s ATT began shifting some of its Long Lines operations away from the New York area. Between 1971 and 1977 both Long Lines headquarters and most of the Administrative workers were relocated to Bedminster, New Jersey. In 1983 the huge International Operating Center in Manhattan was closed, resulting in a major lay-off of traffic workers. Other important changes in company structure and working conditions were a direct result of the court order for ATT divestiture, which took effect January 1, 1984. In 1986 Local 1150's jurisdiction was split, with the creation of CWA Local 1058, representing New Jersey Administrative employees.
Scope and Contents
This collection reflects the complex history of organizing among Long Lines communications workers, from early efforts to shake off ATT paternalism and condescension through the heyday of Local 1150 as a vanguard local of the CWA. Although the strength of the collection is in the period 1949 through the late 1960s, the sparser selection of materials for the pre-CWA period is exceptionally valuable in helping to trace the fledgling New York local through rapid changes in name and structure. The series of Executive Board Minutes begins in 1939, shortly before the creation of the FLLTW. Files of minutes and correspondence and a few agreements dating from the early forties reflect the FLLTW's attempts, with minimal guidance from the National Federation of Telephone Workers, to respond to the exceptional war-time demands of both government and employers. The immediate post-war period, which saw the reconstitution of the local as Local 1 of the new AUTW, is well covered in the Correspondence, Elections, and Contracts series.
Throughout its history --even into the 1970s when automation had drastically reduced the number of operators and other female employees --the New York Long Lines local has been a working partnership between men and women, at all levels of union activity. Not only the role of women as officers but also the concerns of women members are amply illustrated in every part of the collection. Among the outstanding women leaders who are strongly represented in correspondence and other series are Norma F. Naughton, an activist from the early 1930s who held leadership posts in the FFLTW and became the first president of AUTW Local 1 in 1945; Elaine T. Gleason, another long-time activist who served briefly as Local President and left in the late 1950s to become National Director of the CWA's Long Lines Bargaining Unit; Patricia Meckle, who was active in the Traffic Section in the 1950s and went on to serve for many years as Education Chair and then Local Secretary-Treasurer; Clara L. Allen, another Local Secretary-Treasurer, who went on to become New Jersey Area Director, and Angela M. Carroll, Legislative Chair and Secretary-Treasurer in the 1960s.
Male officers whose activity is well documented in the collection include John H. Lotz, Local President 1949-53; George T. Myerscough, Local President 1961-63 and Long Lines Director until 1974, Joseph F. McNiff, former Plant Division Chair who became President in the early 1970s; Morton Bahr, CWA District I Director in the 1970s (from 1985 International President); and Joseph A. Beirne and W. A. Smallwood, who served as CWA International President and Secretary-Treasurer respectively from the early days through most of the period covered by this collection.
While wages and working conditions in general were always central concerns in dealings with management, the pressures of rapid technological and structural change in the industry are also reflected in the Local's energetic struggles over matters of job classification, promotion and reassignment. Conflicts over these issues are particularly prominent in the Elections, Contracts, and Clippings series. The Election records document occasional efforts by groups dissatisfied with the handling of these issues to oppose and unseat the official leadership. They also reflect the discontent, in the 1970s, of the growing body of New Jersey-based Long Lines workers with New York union leadership; the eventual outcome was the formation of a separate NJ Long Lines Local.
Despite gaps in some series, the collection offers excellent opportunities to study important events and issues from a variety of perspectives. For example, the attitude of the local toward participation in the national telephone strike of 1947 can be followed through the Executive Board and committee minutes, through the correspondence of local officers, in election and referendum materials, in the Local's newsletter, and in the very full selection of newspaper clippings for that event. A later cause celebre was the so-called "Hidden Camera Case" of 1963, in which the Local lodged a firm (and successful) protest against management's placing of a camera in a men's washroom after alleged incidents of vandalism there (documented in photographs in the collection's photographs series); local members' and officials' responses to this violation of privacy, and the company's replies, can be traced in the minutes of meetings with management, in members' correspondence, in clippings, and in election publicity materials.
Although the bulk and main emphasis of the collection are to be found in the long series devoted to internal, official workings of the Local and to negotiations with management, there are also some smaller groups of documents which are of exceptional interest. For example, portions of the Minutes and Correspondence series covering the periods of World War II and the Korean War reflect the Local's strenuous efforts to serve members, both on active service and as veterans. The fragmentary records of the Welfare and Social Committees, as well as the file of correspondence with the NYC Central Labor Council, illustrate Local 1150's pioneering programs to promote the health and morale of members and their families. The correspondence file devoted to the Local's political and legislative concerns contains replies from such New York political luminaries as Emmanuel Celler and Adam Clayton Powell and from several U.S. presidents and Secretaries of Labor. The surviving records of Arbitration findings are few, but they reflect a wide variety of issues, from the defense of seniority rights and benefits to women's struggles for equal opportunities in promotion. There are also 45 additional boxes of unprocessed materials that consist of general files and grievances.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into 16 series; most series are arranged chronologically; subject files are arranged alphabetically. Series XVI. 2019 Accretion has not been arranged by an archivist.
I. Charter, By-laws and Constitutions
II. Minutes
III. Correspondence
IV. Election and Referendum Records
V. Financial Records
VI. Bargaining and Arbitration records
VII. Strikes and Work Stoppages
VIII. Convention records
IX: Subject Files
X. Mimeo File
XI. Telephone Tapes, Transcripts
XII. Newsletters, Bulletins, and Clippings
XIII. Unprocessed Material (General Files and Grievances)
XIV. Photographs
XV. Archived Websites
XVI. 2019 Accretion
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Two additional series from this collection, Minutes of the Executive Board, 1939-1978, and several years of Federation Voice (FLLTW) plus a run of Local Spirit, the Local 1150 newsletter, (1950-1985) are available to researchers at the Tamiment Library/ Wagner Labor Archives on microfilm R-7454.
Oral history interviews with a number of members and officers of Local 1150 are available at the Archives on tape. (OH 26)
Records of the Communications Workers of America (WAG 124)
See also the records of CWA, Local 1153 (White Plains, NY), chartered in 1975 (WAG 132). This local was originally part of Local 1150.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the repository email.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Strikes and lockouts -- Telephone companies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Telephone operators |z New York (State) |z New York.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Correspondence.; Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women labor union members -- New York (State) -- New York; Women -- Employment -- New York (State) -- New York; American Union of Telephone Workers.; American Telephone and Telegraph Company. Long Lines Department.; Federation of Long Lines Telephone Workers.; National Federation of Telephone Workers.; Communications Workers of America. Local 1150 (New York, N.Y.); Pratt, James J.; Unger, Laura; Whitley, Vinny
- Series I: Charter, By-laws, and Constitutions, 1944-1984; 546973
  - FLLTW Traffic Branch 101, Charter and By-laws, 1944, undated; 546982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - United Communications Organizations, Proposed Constitution, 1944; 546981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - NFTW, Proposed Constitution for "American Communications Union", 1946; 546980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CWA, Proposed Constituion and By-laws, 1946-1947; 546979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AUTW Local 1, 1949, undated; 546978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CWA Local 1150, 1951-1962; 546977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - CWA Local 1150; Constitution, 1968-1977, 1984, undated; 546976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CWA Local 1150; Constitution, 1979-1980; 546975 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - CWA Local 1150; Constitution, 1983-1984; 546974 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
- Series II: Minutes, 1940-1984; 546905
  - FLLTW Traffic Branch 127, Exec. Board: meetings with management, 1940-1946; 546972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Inter-Union Coordinating Committee, [Sep 1943-Sep 1944]; 546971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - FLLTW Plant Section, Branch 7002, 1945-1946; 546970 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
  - United Communications Organizations, Executive Board (with related correspondence), May 1945-Apr 1946; 546969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - NFTW, Executive Board, Aug 1944, Jun 1945; 546968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Joint Meeting of Telephone Labor Unions in the NYC Area, Aug 17, 1945; 546967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - NFTW, Executive Committee, Branch 101, Oct 4, 1945; 546966 (Box 1, Folder 12a)
  - FLLTW Traffic Branch 101, Exec. Board: meetings with management, 1944-Jun 1946; 546965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - AUTW Local 1, Exec. Board: meetings with management, Jul 1946-1950; 546964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Executive Board, 1970; 546963 (Box 1, Folder 14a)
  - Executive Board, 1978-1979; 546962 (Box 1, Folder 14b)
  - Executive Board, 1980-1981; 546961 (Box 1, Folder 14c)
  - Executive Board, 1982-1983; 546960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Executive Board, 1984-1986; 546959 (Box 1, Folder 14e)
  - CWA Local 1150, Exec. Board: meetings with management (incl.'s notes re: re-employment of veterans), 1952-1954; 546958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - CWA Local 1150, Exec. Board: meetings with management, 1954-1956; 546957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - CWA Local 1150, Exec. Board: meetings with management, 1957-1959; 546956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - CWA Local 1150, Exec. Board: meetings with management (incl.'s 1963 hidden camera incident), 1961-1970; 546955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Traffic Branch 127, membership meetings, 1940; 546954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Traffic Branch 101, membership & supervisors meetings, 1941-1945; 546953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - General Membership meetings (regular and special), 1946-1952; 546952 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General Membership meetings (regular and special), 1957-1964; 546951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General Membership meetings (regular and special), 1967-1979; 546950 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General Membership meetings (regular and special), 1980-1981; 546949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Membership meetings (regular and special), 1982-1984; 546948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Special Membership Meetings, 1958, 1963; 546947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Special Membership Meeting: White Plains, 1960-1962, 1969; 546946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - AUTW Local 1: stewards meetings, [1946-1950]; 546945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Administrative Section, 1946-1957; 546944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Section: stewards mtgs., 1951-1956; 546943 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Plant Section, 1946-1966; 546942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Plant Section: stewards meetings, [1951-1957]; 546941 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Plant Section: meetings with management, 1953; 546940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Traffic Section, Jul 1946-1953; 546939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Traffic Section, 1954-1960; 546938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Traffic Section, 1961-1977, 1983; 546937 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Traffic Section: district stewards meetings, 1948-1954, 1962-1964; 546936 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Traffic Section: stewards meetings, 1947, 1949; 546935 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Traffic Section: meetings with management, 1946-1949; 546934 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Traffic Section: meetings with management, 1950-1953; 546933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Traffic Section: meetings with management, 1955-1962, 1964; 546932 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Traffic Section: meetings with management, 1967-1973; 546931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Long Lines Bargaining, 1954, 1971; 546930 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Grievance Committee, 1947-1948, 1950-1952; 546929 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Grievance Committee, 1953-1954; 546928 (Box 2, Folder 22)